Guide to the Video for Social Change Oral History Collection, 2014 RL.10144
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Video for Social Change Oral History collection
2014
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Center for Documentary Studies
Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
Human Rights Archive (Duke University)
RL.10144
0.5 Linear Feet 1 hard drive (191GB), 1 folder, 1 googledrive link
Video for Social Change was a documentary film course taught by Bruce Orenstein at the Center for Documentary Studies in the spring of 2014. The collection includes eight interviews, with North Carolina social justice activists James Andrews, Rukiya Dillahunt, Anita Earls, Angaza Laughinghouse, Dani Moore, Allison Riggs, Melinda Wiggins, and Mel Williams. The materials in the collection include camera footage in AVCHD format, edited master videos in MP4 format, transcripts, and releases for eight interviews.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Collection Overview
Video for Social Change was a documentary film course taught by Bruce Orenstein at the Center for Documentary Studies in the spring of 2014. Focusing on the production of advocacy videos for social change, the course introduced knowledge and skill sets needed to make effective videos for grassroots organizations, exploring how video is integrated into organizing strategies to achieve better results. Student projects consisted of video oral histories with social justice advocates in North Carolina, including James Andrews, Rukiya Dillahunt, Anita Earls, Angaza Laughinghouse, Dani Moore, Allison Riggs, Melinda Wiggins, and Mel Williams. The materials in the collection Include raw footage, edited projects, transcripts, and releases.
Poverty -- North Carolina; Video recordings; Migrant agricultural laborers -- North Carolina; Suffrage -- North Carolina; North Carolina -- Social conditions; Audiovisual materials; Civil rights -- North Carolina; Oral histories (document genre); Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Human Rights Archive (Duke University)
- Interviews, Spring 2014
  Scope and Contents
  The video interviews and accompanying transcripts were created digitally. You may view streaming copies of the edited video masters under each interview listed below. To access the original video resources and transcripts, contact Rubenstein Library Research Services.
  - James Andrews interviewed by Harish Chatrathi, 2014 February 28; 104 minutes
    President of the North Carolina state AFL CIO Federation, James Andrews grew up in segregated Warren County, North Carolina, and was awarded the Purple Heart for wounds sustained during his service in the Vietnam War. Andrews discusses his career as a union organizer and his rise in the ranks of the AFL CIO. He also discusses the labor and the state of unions today and their future challenges. -- Description adapted from interview abstract (see Transcript).
    - Edited MP4 master, 2014 February 28
    - AVCHD camera original, 2014 February 28
    - Transcript, 2014 February 28
    - Release, 2014 February 28
  - Rukiya Dillahunt interviewed by Nandini Srinivasan, 2014 February 19; 117 minutes
    Rukiya Dillahunt is a retired educator and active advocate. She grew up in Charleston, South Carolina, and received her undergraduate degree from West Virginia State University. In this interview, Rukiya discusses her experience organizing with Black Workers for Justice, as well as her tenure as a teacher and assistant principal in the Wake County School System. She also provides insight about the school-to-prison pipeline and its implications for North Carolina's youth. Rukiya is married to Ajamu Dillahunt, another prominent organizer and advocate. -- Description taken from interview abstract (see Transcript).
    - Edited MP4 master, 2014 February 19
    - AVCHD camera original, 2014 February 19
    - Transcript, 2014 February 19
    - Release, 2014 February 19
  - Anita Earls interviewed by Michele Spencer and Esther Kim, 2014 March 03; 109 minutes
    Civil rights attorney and Executive Director of the Southern Coalition for Social Justice, Anita Earls grew up in a mixed race family in the 1960s. In this interview she discusses how her family background and the environment informed her career, and gives her perspective on issues surrounding voting rights in North Carolina and the nation. -- Description adapted from interview abstract (see Transcript).
    - Edited MP4 master, 2014 February 19
    - AVCHD camera original, 2014 March 03
    - Transcript, 2014 February 19
    - Release, 2014 February 19
  - Angaza Laughinghouse interviewed by Marcus Montaño and Lauren Gerald., 2014 March 06; 105 minutes
    Angaza Laughinghouse is a founder of the political organization Black Workers for Justice based in Raleigh, North Carolina. Laughinghouse first got involved in activism in New York where he grew up, before moving to North Carolina after hearing about the Charlotte Three and the Wilmington Ten. He began community and workplace organizing after the Greensboro Massacre. Black Workers for Justice came to be as a result of protests against unfair treatment of female workers at a K-Mart in Rocky Mount. The organization strives to empower workers to stand up for their own needs both in the workplace and in the community. They have also been active in political campaigns and have had members run for office. -- Description adapted from interview abstract (see Transcript).
    - Edited MP4 master, 2014 March 06
    - AVCHD camera original, 2014 March 06
    - Transcript, 2014 March 06
    - Release, 2014 March 06
  - Dani Moore interviewed by Rinchen Dolma, 2014 February 25; 95 minutes
    Director of the Immigrant Rights Project at the North Carolina Justice Center, Dani Moore grew up in Tarboro, North Carolina, and earned a B.A. in Economics from Wake Forest University and a master's degree from Harvard Divinity School. In this oral history, she talks about growing up in a poor family in Tarboro, touching on interracial differences and their complicated relationships in her community and school. She also discusses her experiences with different organizations in social justice advocacy. -- Description adapted from interview abstract (see Transcript).
    Conditions Governing Access
    Video and transcript of interview is restricted to reading room use only until 2024.
    - Edited MP4 master, 2014 February 25
    - AVCHD camera original, 2014 February 25
    - Transcript, 2014 February 25
    - Release, 2014 February 25
  - Allison Riggs interviewed by Eric Adams, 2014 February 28; 108 minutes
    Allison Riggs is a staff attorney for the Southern Coalition for Social Justice who focuses mainly on voting rights. Riggs grew up in Morgantown, West Virginia and received her undergraduate and graduate education from the University of Florida. In her interview, she discusses her current work on voting rights and issues surrounding redistricting, Section 5 of the Civil Rights Act of 1965 in the state of North Carolina, and the impact that Supreme Court cases regarding voting legislation have had on North Carolina and the country as a whole. She also discusses other problematic discriminatory occurrences in North Carolina, such as police discrimination and profiling, and the subsequent collateral damages that occur from these practices. -- Description adapted from interview abstract (see Transcript).
    - Edited MP4 master, 2014 February 28
    - AVCHD camera original, 2014 February 28
    - Transcript, 2014 February 28
  - Melinda Wiggins interviewed by Amy Trey and Christine Delp, 2014 February 24; 120 minutes
    Executive director of the Durham, North Carolina-based Student Action with Farmworkers, Melinda Wiggins grew up in the Mississippi Delta. Melinda attend Millsaps College and later Duke Divinity School, where she explored different types of advocacy work before turning to farmworker rights. In this interview, Melinda reflects upon her own development as an activist, as well as the specifics of farmworker advocacy work in North Carolina and the South. -- Description adapted from interview abstract (see Transcript).
    - Edited MP4 master, 2014 February 24
    - AVCHD camera original, 2014 February 24
    - Transcript, 2014 February 24
    - Release, 2014 February 24
  - Mel Williams interviewed by Batya Knebel and Sam Selig in chinese, 2014 March 04; 106 minutes
    Reverend Mel Williams's career began during the 1960s, shaped by the civil rights movement and his interest in fighting poverty in Durham, North Carolina. As a pastor of the Watts Street Baptist Church, Williams gathered together diverse communities to bring awareness to the city's poor. Reverend Williams' work includes the Congregations Coalition, End Poverty Durham, the Walltown "Neighbor to Neighbor" mission, and the Coalition for Non-Violent Durham. In this interview, Williams shares his thoughts on his work, including inspirational moments and the spiritual sources inspiring him. -- Description adapted from interview abstract (see Transcript).
    - Edited MP4 master, 2014 March 04
    - AVCHD camera original, 2014 March 04
    - Transcript, 2014 March 04
    - Release, 2014 March 04